Guide to the John Gerassi Papers ALBA.018
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Gerassi Papers
1979-1983, 2000s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gerassi, John
ALBA.018
11.25 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes and 7 record cartons
Journalist and scholar John ("Tito") Gerassi received his MA at Columbia University and earned his doctorate at the London School of Economics. Among his publications are The Great Fear in Latin America (1965), The Boys of Boise (1966), and the biography Jean-Paul Sartre: Hated Conscience of His Century (1989). The Premature Anti-Fascists: Oral History of American and Canadian Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War was published in 1986, and is a tribute to the men and women who volunteered to fight on behalf of the Spanish Republic. This collection consists chiefly of full transcriptions of 65 of the oral histories that were conducted for Gerassi's project (with supporting research materials) and unprocessed materials relating to Gerassi's research on Jean-Paul Sartre.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of oral history transcripts from Gerassi's project, The Premature Anti-Fascists: Oral History of American and Canadian Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, as well as materials used by Gerassi in the course of researching and writing the book. The collection also contains research conducted for his books on Jean-Paul Sartre.
Custodial History
The John Gerassi Collection was donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in three separate accessions. The bulk of the material was donated by John Gerassi in 1983. Subsequent donations were made by Betsy Gimbel in 1988 and by Ray Villis in 1997. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. In 2012, an additional donation was made to NYU's collection by John Gerassi's daughter, Lara.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Journalist and scholar John ("Tito") Gerassi was born in France in July 1931, to Fernando Gerassi, a Turkish-born artist of Sephardic Jewish heritage, and Ukranian born Stepha Awdykowicz. Moving between Barcelona and Paris, the couple belonged to the cosmopolitan circle of artists and intellectuals who congregated in cafes to argue art and politics, and counted Jean-Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir as close friends. When civil war broke out in Spain in 1936, Fernando Gerassi joined the Loyalist forces. He served as a general in the Spanish Army and became the inspiration for the figure of Gomez, the artist and revolutionary in Sartre's trilogy Roads to Freedom. Following the Fascist victory in Spain, the Gerassi family emigrated to the United States in 1940. John Gerassi was raised in New York City and attended Columbia University. He spent a decade in journalism, worked as an editor for Time and, later, Newsweek before serving as a foreign correspondent for the New York Times. He left journalism to pursue a career in academia and earned his doctorate at the London School of Economics. He was an instructor at the John Kennedy Freedom School in Berlin and at the University of California at Irvine before joining the faculty of Queens College of the City University of New York in 1978. Among his publications are The Great Fear in Latin America (1965); The Boys of Boise (1966); the biography Jean-Paul Sartre: Hated Conscience of His Century (1989); and "The Comintern, the Fronts and the CPUSA," in New Studies in the Politics and Culture of U.S. Communism (1993).
His father's death in 1974 and his own subsequent journey to Barcelona the following year kindled his interest in the Spanish Civil War and the men and woman who volunteered to fight on behalf of the Republic. The Premature Anti-Fascists: Oral History of American and Canadian Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, Gerassi's tribute to these volunteers, was published in 1986. In the preface to that work, he describes his methodology for selecting and recording the oral histories that became the foundation for his study. In the spring of 1979, Gerassi sent out one-page questionnaires to 300 U.S. and Canadian veterans of the Spanish Civil War:
"From the 210 answers, I selected 50 absolute 'musts' to be personally interviewed. By making another 100 phone calls, I chose another 30. And 50 more were picked along the way, either by Mr. Ray Villis, my principal interviewer, or by myself and Ms. Chantal Ferraro, my main researcher…. Of the 130 interviewed, 65 were fully transcribed; the rest were used for background verification. The resulting 18,000 pages were then edited down by me…. Rather than fill scores of pages with tridots, brackets, and explanatory footnotes, I took the liberty of editing the interviews so that each section could read smoothly as a narrative."
Although the study is a sympathetic and admiring portrait of the veterans as a group, and Gerassi took pains to remain true to the intent and voice of the individual accounts, some of the veterans were displeased with Gerassi's polished edits of their oral histories.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged alphabetically by name. Series II is arranged alphabetically by topic. Series III is unprocessed.
Organized into three series:
Missing Title
Series I: Oral History Transcripts
Series II: Subject Files
Series III: Unprocessed Materials
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archie Brown Papers, ALBA #207.
John Gerassi Oral History Collection, ALBA Audio #18
Vincent Lossowski Papers, ALBA #71.
Irving Weissman Papers, ALBA #165.
Alvah Bessie Papers, ALBA #24.
Robert Colodny Papers, ALBA #211.
Separated Material
Photographs and audiotapes from the John Gerassi Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives. Approximately one linear foot of personal materials from the 2012 accretion was returned to the Gerassi family.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information, to request digitization of materials, and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Biography; Drafts (documents); Articles.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- African Americans; Oral history.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Research (document genres).; Ornitz, Lou, 1912-1984; Brown, Archie, 1911-1990.; Kea, Salaria (O'Reilly); Harris, Sydney, 1916-; Goff, Irving; Stamm, Morris; Weissman, Irving, 1913-1998; Gladnick, Robert; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Scheutrum, Walter; Wolff, Milton.; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Marzani, Carl; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Fishman, Mosess (Moe), 1916-2007; Hutchins, Evelyn, 1910-1982; Pistone, Rosario.; Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003; Kilpatrick, Admiral; Bailey, Bill, 1911-1995; Steck, Robert; Dent, Walter; Felsen, Milt, 1912-2005; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Colodny, Robert Garland.; Geiser, Carl; Gates, John, 1913-1992; Watt, George, 1913-1994; Hunter, Oscar; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Rosenstein, Herman, 1915-; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Lossowski, Vincent, 1914-1984; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980; Murra, John V.; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993
- Series I: Oral History Transcripts
  Scope and Content Note
  This series is made up of full transcriptions of 65 of the oral histories that were conducted for Gerassi's project. Included here are transcripts for the following individuals: Bill Bailey, Alvah Bessie, Robert Colodny, Archie Brown, Walter Dent, Milt Felsen, Moe Fishman, John Gates, Carl Geiser, Robert Gladnick, Irving Goff, Syd Harris, Oscar Hunter, Evelyn Hutchins, Salaria Kee (a.k.a. Salaria Kea) O'Reilly, Admiral Kilpatrick, Edward Lending, Vincent Lossowski, Carl Marzani, John Murra, Steve Nelson, Lou Ornitz, Rosario Pistone, Herman Rosenstein (a.k.a. Gabby Klein), Walter Scheutrum, Morris Stamm, Robert Steck, George Watt, Irving Weissman, and Milton Wolff.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted.
  - Bailey, Bill, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bailey, Bill (corrected by Bailey), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benet, James, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bessie, Alvah, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bessie, Alvah (w/corrections by Dan Bessie), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bonetti, Frank, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brennan, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Archie, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cohen, Milt, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Colodny, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Colodny, Robert (corrected by Colodny), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Colow, Murray, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dent, Walter, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Edwards, Lionel, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Felsen, Milt, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fishman, Moe, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Forbes, Alex, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Forester, Clarence, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gates, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Geiser, Carl, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gladnick, Robert (Tape 1 Side A through Tape 3 side F), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gladnick, Robert (Tape 4 Side G through Tape 7 Side N), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Goff, Irving, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Groden, Daniel, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Halonen, Oiva, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Harris, Sidney, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hunter, Oscar, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hutchins, Evelyn, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kilpatrick, Admiral, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kish, Leslie, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lamb, Leonard, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Landis, Art, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Liversedge, Ron, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lloyd, Thomas, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lossowski, Vincent, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lossowski, Vincent; Lending, Ed; Miller, David, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - McElligot, John Paddy, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - MacLeod, Donald, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Maki, Martin, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Markert, Clement, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Markert, Clement (corrected by Markert), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Markert, Clement (revised by the interviewee), undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Marzani, Carl, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mattersdorfer, Fred, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Murra, John, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Nelson, Steve, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Nelson Steve (corrections and notes by Nelson), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Noble, Harry, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Norris, Len, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - O'Reilly, Salaria Kee (a.k.a. Salaria Kea), undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - O'Reilly, Salaria Kee (a.k.a. Salaria Kea) (duplicate), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ornitz, Lou, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Osheroff, Abe, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Penrod, John, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Penrod, John (duplicate), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Pistone, Rosario, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Prago, Al, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Reed, Robert, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Rintz, Norman, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Rosenstein, Herman, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Rossen, John, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Russell, Ross, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Schmidt, Norman James, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Shantzek, Mike, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Skolnick, Abraham, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Slater, Carl, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Sorensen, Henning, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Stamm, Morris, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Stamm, Morris (radio interview), undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Steck, Bob, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Susman, Bill, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tisa, John and May, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Watt, George, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Weissman, Irving, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Weissman, Irving (corrected), undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Wellman, Saul (version 1 with edits), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Wellman, Saul (version 2 with edits), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Wolff, Milt, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series II: Subject Files
  This series consists of clippings, articles, biographical files, research photocopies of correspondence from the Spanish Civil War-era, and some correspondence between Gerassi and individual veterans. Gerassi used these materials in the course of researching and writing his book. A file related to the Rockefeller Foundation grant received by Gerassi to fund this project can also be found here.
  - American Veterans: Contact Sheets, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bailey, Bill, undated, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Canadian Veterans: Contact Sheets, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Canadian Volunteers: Government Records, 1937-1938 (photocopies), undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Cartoons about Snipers, signed A.H.L. (photocopies), undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Cohen, Milt, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Fajardo, Jose M.: "The International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War" ( Mundo Obrero article), 1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Herrick, William, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Larrando, Pacho Fernandez: "Foreigners and Strangers in the Civil War" ( Mucho Obrero article), undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Lending, Ed: Correspondence (photocopies 1937, 1961-1979; originals 1980), undated, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Liversedge, Ronald (Canadian): Spanish Civil War Memoir, 1965 (photocopied typescript)., undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - MacEachron, Paul: Correspondence (photocopy, 1937), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Mykola, Kit: Memoir (Canadian Volunteer), undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Päviö, Jules (Finnish-Canadian Volunteer), 1981 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Poem [Scab]: Author Unknown, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Grant: Correspondence and Expense Reports, 1981-1983 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Robel, Charles Edward: Clippings (photocopies, undated, 1934-1938, 1976) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Robel, Charles Edward: Correspondence (photocopies, 1937), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Robel Family: Correspondence (photocopies, 1929-1937), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Sennett, William: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Smith, Randall (Pete), undated, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Spanish Refugee Aid, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Stamm, Morris: Clippings and Legal Documents (photocopies, 1949, 1977-1978), undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Trotsky, Leon and Bertram Wolfe: Correspondence (research photocopies, 1936-1937), undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Veterans: Annotated List, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - VALB: Historical Commission Bulletin, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - VALB: Questionnaires: Midwestern and West Coast Veterans, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - VALB: Questionnaires: Northeastern Veterans, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Watt, George, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Weissman, Irving, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Wellman, Saul, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Yaroshchuk, Yosyp, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Series III: Unprocessed Materials, 1940s-2000s
  The unprocessed materials consist of federal government documents on John Gerassi and his family obtained through the Freedom of Information Act in the 1970s; subject files on various political topics, mainly from the 1970s; Gerassi's research and publicity materials for his biographies of Jean-Paul Sartre; Gerassi's articles and unpublished writings from the late 1960s-late 1980s; biographical materials; and loose news articles collected in the 2000s on a variety of political topics (some with annotations). There are also two reels of microfilm from the Hoover Institution labeled "Nuestra Industria Revista Economica" and approximately 50 cassette tapes, some on Sartre and some labeled "personal" or "political."
  - Unprocessed Materials, 1940s-2000s (Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17)